James A. Pike Papers
James A. Pike Papers
- Writings
  - Articles
    - "Liberal" in "The Spectrum of Protestant Belief" Robert Campbell, ed., Sign, Jan 1968; published material (Box 84)
    - "The Liturgy and Work" from Liturgy Is Mission, published material (Box 84)
    - "Living in Peace With Our Contemporaries" The Optimist Magazine, Jul 1964; published material (Box 84)
    - "The Lockout of God in Our Public Schools" Family Weekly, Oct 1962; published material (Box 84)
    - "Love, Sex and Marriage" Compact, Oct 1956; published material (Box 84)
    - "Marry A Roman Catholic?" Link, Sep 1963; published material; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - "The Meaning and the Need of Reformation" in various denominational magazines, Oct 1957; published material; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - "The Ministry and Church Unity -- Roadblock or Avenue?", draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy; draft C, typescript copy revised; 3 folders (Box 84)
    - "Morality in the Secular City", draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - "Never On Monday" Ladies Home Journal, 1962; typescript copy revised (Box 84)
    - "Notes On the Problem of Theological Communication", 1951?; typescript revised (Box 84)
    - "Old Presbytery Done Small" Christian Century, May 1959; published material (Box 84)
    - "On Taking Risks", 1957; typescript copy (Box 84)
    - "Pacem in Terris and the World Community" Continuum, Summer 1963; published material (Box 84)
    - "Pastoral Letter Regarding 'Speaking in Tongues,'" Pastoral Psychology, May 1964; published material (Box 84)
    - "The Place of Religion in a University" Union Seminary Quarterly Review, Mar 1950; draft A, printed material; draft B; published material; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - "Pluralism in the College" SPA Newsletter, May 1951; printed material (Box 84)
    - "Planned Parenthood in New York" Living Church, Feb 1953; published material (Box 84)
    - "The Problem of Mixed Marriages" condensed from If You Marry Outside Your Faith, 1955?; draft A, galley rev.; draft B, typescript copy revised; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - "The Purpose of The University" UCLA Alumni Magazine, Oct 1960; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy (Box 84)
    - "The Real Object of Prayer" taken from The Next Day, 1958; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - "Reformation Day Message" in various denominational magazines, Oct 1955; published material (Box 84)
    - "Religion and Materialism in America", galley revised (Box 84)
    - "Religion and Show Business" New York Herald-Tribune, TV and Radio Magazine, Jun 1957?; published material (Box 84)
    - "Religion and the State" Living Church, Aug 1948; published material (Box 84)
    - "Religion in Higher Education and the Problem of Pluralism" Christianity and Crisis, Jan 1951; typescript revised; published material; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - "Religions in Israel" from Mandelbaum, Bernard, ed., Assignment In Israel, NY: Harper and Bros., published material (Box 84)
    - "The Right to be an Atheist" Coronet, Apr 1961; draft A (incomplete), typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy revised, and holograph; draft C, typescript revised; published material; 4 folders (Box 84)
    - "The Role of Music in the Changing Church" with Alec Wyton, Music, Mar 1968; published material (Box 84)
    - "The Roots of Bias" Look, Mar 1961; drafts A-D, typescripts and typescript copies, some with revisions; published material; 5 folders (Box 84)
    - "Should A Catholic Be President?" Life, Dec 1959; drafts A and B, typescripts and typescript copies, with revisions; published material; 3 folders (Box 84)
    - "Should a Catholic Be President?" Reader's Digest, Mar 1960; published material (Box 84)
    - "Should A Catholic Be President?" ("A Catholic for President?" reprinted by Evangelical-United Brethren Church), published material (Box 84)
    - "Should the Pulpit Be a Rostrum?" New York Times Magazine, Aug 1960; typescript copy revised; published material; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - "So Maybe You're Normal" Family Circle, Sep 1956; typescript copy; published material; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - "The Sputniks and Our Anxiety" To Our Friends, Jan 1958; drafts A-E, typescripts, typescript copies, B has revisions; published material; 6 folders (Box 84)
    - "The Sputniks and Our Anxiety" The Bulletin (The Divinity School of the Protestant Episcopal Church in Philadelphia), published material (Box 84)
    - "The Supreme Court and Increasing Polarization Within the Churches", 1969; research material; published material reproduction; typescript; 2 folders (Box 85)
    - "Tax Organized Religion" Playboy, Apr 1967; printed material annotated (Box 85)
    - "Tax Organized Religion" Stewardship Facts 1968/69, published material (Box 85)
    - "Ten Things That Make Christmas Really Christmas" McCall's, Dec 1959; printed material (Box 85)
    - "'That They May Be One,'" Christian Century, Jan 1960; typescript copy; published material; 2 folders (Box 85)
    - "Timeless Ground of Freedom" The Witness, Dec 1958; published material (Box 85)
    - "Three-pronged Synthesis" Christian Century, Dec 1960; draft A, typescript copy; draft B, typescript copy revised; published material revised; 4 folders (Box 85)
    - "To Charles Van Doren" Christian Century, Dec 1959; typescript (Box 85)
    - "The U.S. Is In A Goldfish Bowl" Think, typescript copy (Box 85)
    - "We're Back" The Owl (Univ. of Santa Clara), 1970; published material reproduction (Box 85)
    - "What Are The Limits of Dissent?" Center Magazine, typescript reproduction (Box 85)
    - "What Has Happened To Our Morality?" New York Times Magazine, Jun 1962; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy; revised; published material; 3 folders (Box 85)
    - "What Is the World's Greatest Need?" New York Times Magazine, Apr 1961; published material (Box 85)
    - "What Is Doctrinal Orthodoxy?" The Witness, Mar 1961; published material (Box 85)
    - "What Will the World Be like in 1987?" Look, Jan 1962; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy; published material; 3 folders (Box 85)
    - "What You Don't Know About Your Minister" in This Week and Lutheran Digest, 1957; 1958; drafts A and B, typescript copies revised; published material; 4 folders (Box 85)
    - "When Your Child Doubts God" Family Weekly, Aug 1959; published material (Box 85)
    - "Where Do You Go When You Die?" Pageant, Apr 1961; published material (Box 85)
    - "Why I Got Married Twice" Parade, Jul 1957; typescript copy; published material; 2 folders (Box 85)
    - "Why I'm Leaving the Church" Look, Apr 1969
      - Research material, published material (Box 85)
      - Outline, holograph, incomplete typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 85)
      - Drafts A-J, typescripts and typescript copies, some with revisions; holographs; 10 folders (Box 85)
      - Galleys, revised, 4 folders (Box 85)
      - Published material (Box 85)
    - "Why Stay On Board" Center Magazine, 1968; draft A, typescript and holograph; draft B, typescript reproduction; 2 folders (Box 85)
    - "Why There Are Bigots" New York Times Magazine, Oct 30, 1960; typescript copy revised and typescript reproduction; galleys, revised; published material; 4 folders (Box 85)
    - "Your Ministry and Your Laymen's Ministry" Princeton Seminary Bulletin, Oct 1956; published material (Box 85)
    - Untitled
      - On Bible quotation, This Week, Feb 1957; published material (Box 85)
      - On bigoted publications, New York Times, 1960; typescript copy revised (Box 85)
      - On Christmas, typescript (Box 85)
      - On church decline, Psychology Today, typescript reproduction and typescript (Box 85)
      - On decline of religious influence, typescript (Box 85)
      - On diocesan customary, Witness, draft A, typescript copy revised; draft B (incomplete), typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 85)
      - On missionary to China, St. Ambrose, and forgiveness, for AP News features, 1957; typescript copy (Box 85)
      - On nuclear shelters, Los Gatos Times-Observer, Feb 1961; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy; published material; 3 folders (Box 85)
      - On presbytery, Overseas Mission Review, 1959; draft A, typescript and published material, with revisions; draft B, typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 85)
      - On Protestant Reformation, Jul 1957; typescript copy revised (Box 85)
      - On Vatican II and church unity, New York Times Magazine, Sep-Oct 1962; drafts A and B, typescript copies, with revisions; 3 folders (Box 85)
      - On violence, 1968; typescript repro, rev. (Box 85)
    - Miscellaneous published material (Box 85)
  - Book reviews
    - Barth, Karl, Call For God, in Chicago Sun-Times, Oct 1967; typescript reproduction rev., published material (Box 85)
    - Blau, Joseph L., ed., Cornerstones of Religious Freedom in America, 1949?; drafts A, B, C typescript copies, some with revisions; 3 folders (Box 86)
    - Borchard, Edwin, Declaratory Judgements, 1943; published material (Box 86)
    - Brunner, Emil, The Great Invitation, typescript revised (Box 86)
    - Butterfield, Herbert, History and Human Relations, in New York Times Book Review, typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Cailliet, Emile, The Dawn of Personality, typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Casserley, J. V. Langmead, The Christian in Philosophy, typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Commission on Communism, General Assembly of the Church of Scotland, Second Report, The Church Under Communism, 1953?; typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Davies, A.P., The Urge To Persecute, in New York Herald-Tribune, Mar 1954; published material (Box 86)
    - Davies, D.R., On To Orthodoxy, in New York Times Book Review, published material (Box 86)
    - Dobie, Armistead and Ladd, Mason, Cases and Materials on Federal Jurisdiction and Procedure, typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Eliot, T.S., Notes Towards the Definition of Culture, The Cocktail Party, typescript revised (Box 86)
    - Fromm, Erich, You Shall Be As Gods, 1966; typescript carbon (Box 86)
    - Gaebelin, Frank, Christian Education in a Democracy, in Living Church, Jun 1951; fragments, typescript revised and typescript copy; published material (Box 86)
    - Heuss, John, Our Christian Vocation, 1955?; typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Hutchinson, John A., ed., Christian Faith and Social Action, 1953?; typescript copy revised (Box 86)
    - De Jesus-Marie, Bruno, ed., Satan, in New York Times Book Review, 1952; draft A, holograph; draft B, typescript revised; draft C, typescript copy; published material; 4 folders (Box 86)
    - Pope John XXIII, Pacem in Terris, typescript copy revised (Box 86)
    - Kellen, Horace M., Secularism is the Will of God, typescript copy revised (Box 86)
    - Lamprecht, Sterling P., Our Religious Traditions, in New York Times Book Review and in Witness, 1950; typescript copies revised; published material; 3 folders (Box 86)
    - Lehmann, Rosamond, The Swan In The Evening, in Saturday Review, Jun 1968; typescript reproduction revised; published material; 2 folders (Box 86)
    - Lockhart, John Gilbert, Cosmo Gordon Lang, drafts A and B, typescript copies; 2 folders (Box 86)
    - Loos, A. William, ed., Religious Faith and World Culture, in New York Times Book Review, May 1952; published material (Box 86)
    - McKnight, John P., The Papacy: A New Appraisal, typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Marcel, Gabriel, Man Against Mass Society, in New York Times Book Review, Feb 1953; typescript copy; published material; 2 folders (Box 86)
    - Marchant, Sir James, ed., The Coming-of-Age of Christianity, in New York Times Book Review, Oct 1951; published material (Box 86)
    - Merton, Thomas, The Ascent to Truth, in New York Times Book Review, Sep 1951; holograph; published material; 2 folders (Box 86)
    - Merton, Thomas, Bread In The Wilderness, Jan 1954; typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Micklem, Nathaniel, Law and the Laws, in Theology Today, 1952; typescript copy revised (Box 86)
    - Miller, Perry, Calhoun, Robert L., Pusey, Nathan M. and Niebuhr, Reinhold, Religion and Freedom of Thought, typescript revised (Box 86)
    - Nash, Arnold S., ed., Protestant Thought in the Twentieth Century, in New York Times Book Review, Aug 1951; published material (Box 86)
    - O'Faolain, Sean, Newman's Way: The Odyssey of John Henry Newman, 1952; typescript copy revised (Box 86)
    - Overstreet, H.A., The Great Enterprise, in New York Times, Aug 1952; published material (Box 86)
    - Oxnam, G. Bromley, I Protest, typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Pelikan, Jaraslov, The Riddle of Roman Catholicism, in Life, typescript copy revised (Box 86)
    - Phillips, J.B. Plain Christianity, drafts A, B, holograph; draft C, typescript copy with revisions; 3 folders (Box 86)
    - Phillips, J.B. Your God Is Too Small, Sep 1952; typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Pilpel, Harriet F. and Zalvin, Theodora, Your Marriage and the Law, typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Ramsay, A.M., Sacred and Secular and Thornton, Martin, The Rock and the River, in New Christian, Dec 1965; published material (Box 86)
    - Ramsey, Paul, Basic Christian Ethics, in New York Times Book Review, Feb 1951; published material (Box 86)
    - Religion and the Intellectuals, in New York Times Book Review, 1950; drafts A and B, typescript copy, B has revisions; published material; 3 folders (Box 86)
    - Rock, John, The Time Has Come, in Living Church, Oct 1953; typescript copy; published material; 2 folders (Box 86)
    - Roy, Ralph Lord, Apostles of Discord, in New York Herald-Tribune, typescript copy (Box 86)
    - "Rynne, Xavier" The Third Session, typescript revised (Box 86)
    - Sheen, Fulton J., Three to Get Married, in New York Times Book Review, Jun 1951; published material (Box 86)
    - Simon, Paul and Jeanne, Protestant-Catholic Marriages Can Succeed, typescript reproduction (Box 86)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, Church and State in the United States, in New York Times Book Review, May 1950; drafts A and B, typescript copy, A has revisions; published material; 3 folders (Box 86)
    - Stryker, Lloyd Paul, The Art of Advocacy, typescript copy revised (Box 86)
    - Switz, Theodore M., Communism and Christianity, 1953; typescript copy revised (Box 86)
    - Teller, Judd L., The Kremlin, The Jews and the Middle East, May 1957; typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Tettemer, John, I Was A Monk, Mabie, Janet, ed., published material (Box 86)
    - Toynbee, Arnold, An Historian's Approach to Religion, in New York Times Book Review, Sep 1956; draft, typescript; published material; 2 folders (Box 86)
    - Underwood, Kenneth W., Protestant and Catholic, draft A, typescript copy revised; draft B, typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Walsh, Chad, Campus Gods on Trial, in New York Times Book Review, May 1953; drafts A and B, typescript, typescript copy, holograph, with revisions; published material; 3 folders (Box 86)
    - Wright, Richardson, A Book of Days for Christians, typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Wu, John C.H., The Fountain of Justice, in Northwestern University Law Review, Jan-Feb 1957; typescript copy revised; published material; 2 folders (Box 86)
    - Miscellaneous comments on books, 1957-1958; typescript copy (Box 86)
    - Miscellaneous short reviews, 1953; 1955 (Box 86)
  - Books
    The collection originally contained a number of published editions of books by Pike, or to which Pike contributed. These have been rransferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
    - Beyond Anxiety
      - Book reviews, 1953; typescript; published material (Box 86)
      - Suggested corrections, typescript (Box 86)
    - Beyond Death
      - Foreword, 1955?; typescript revised (Box 86)
      - Proposed contents, 1955; typescript (Box 86)
    - Beyond the Law, Julius Rosenthal Lectures, 1963
      - Draft A, typescript/typescript copy revised (Box 86)
      - Draft B, typescript/typescript copy revised (Box 87)
      - Galley page proofs (Box 87)
      - Book reviews, published material (Box 87)
    - Cases and Other Materials on New Federal and Code Procedure, 1940; book review; published material (Box 87)
    - The Church, Politics, and Society, with John Pyle, 1955; book reviews; published material (Box 87)
    - Doing The Truth
      See also Writings: Miscellaneous: "Doing The Truth".
      - Prospectus, typescript copy (Box 87)
      - Chapter II, "Religion and Ethics", typescript copy (Box 87)
      - Excerpts, typescript, typescript copy (Box 87)
      - Book reviews, 1955; typescript, typescript copy; published material (Box 87)
    - The Faith of the Church, with Norman Pittenger
      - Preface, 1951; typescript copy revised (Box 87)
      - Chapter IV (incomplete), 1951; typescript copy (Box 87)
      - Prospectus, 1949; typescript copy (Box 87)
      - Book reviews, 1952; published material (Box 87)
    - The Fourth "R": Religion in Education Today, outline, typescript revised, and holograph (Box 87)
    - How To Face Life, 1957; book reviews; typescript copy; published material (Box 87)
    - I Believe [unpublished?], 1961
      - Foreword, typescript (Box 87)
      - Chapter I, fragments; drafts A-C, typescript copies; 3 folders (Box 87)
      - Chapter II, typescript copy revised (Box 87)
      - Chapter III, typescript annotated (Box 87)
      - Chapter ?, "He Ascended into Heaven", typescript (Box 87)
      - Chapter ?, "The Resurrection of the Body" (Box 87)
      - Chapter ?, "The World of the Life to Come", typescript revised (Box 87)
    - If This Be Heresy
      See also Writings: Miscellaneous: If This Be Heresy - new epilog.
      - Chapters I-VIII, 1967; printer's copy, typescript; 2 folders (Box 87)
      - Book reviews, 1967; published material (Box 88)
    - If You Marry Outside Your Faith
      - Suggested changes by readers, typescript, typescript copy (Box 88)
      - Miscellaneous additional material, typescript (Box 88)
      - Index, typescript copy (Box 88)
      - Book reviews, 1954; typescript copy; published material (Box 88)
    - Man In The Middle, with Howard A. Johnson
      - Book reviews, 1956; published material (Box 88)
    - Modern Canterbury Pilgrims
      - Research material, typescript copy, typescript revised (Box 88)
      - Book reviews, 1956; published material (Box 88)
    - A New Look At Preaching, George Craig Stewart Memorial Lectures
      - Introduction, 1960; draft A, typescript copy; draft B, typescript revised; 2 folders (Box 88)
      - Chapter I, 1960; drafts A-C, typescripts, some with revisions; printer's copy, typescript; 5 folders (Box 88)
      - Chapter II, 1960; drafts A-C (incomplete); typescripts, typescript copies, some with revisions; printer's copy, typescript; 3 folders (Box 88)
      - Chapter III, 1960; draft, typescript copy; draft fragments, typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 88)
      - Chapter IV, 1960; draft A, typescript; draft B, typescript copy revised; 2 folders (Box 88)
      - Complete draft, 1960; typescript copy revised (Box 88)
      - Galley, revised, 1961 (Box 88)
      - Book reviews, 1961; published material (Box 88)
    - The Next Day [?]
      - Drafts, A (incomplete), typescript copy; B (incomplete), typescript copy revised; 2 folders (Box 88)
      - Lists of possible titles, recipients of complimentary copies, 1957; typescript (Box 88)
      - Book reviews, 1957; published material (Box 88)
      - Excerpts syndicated to newspapers, 1958 (Box 88)
    - The Other Side, with Diane Kennedy
      - Foreword, 1968; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy (Box 89)
      - Chapter I, 1967; draft A, typescript revised; draft B (incomplete), typescript revised and holograph; draft C, typescript repro revised; draft D, typescript revised; 4 folders (Box 89)
      - Chapter II, 1967; draft, typescript revised, and holograph (Box 89)
      - Chapter III, 1967; draft (incomplete), typescript revised; draft fragments, typescript revised; 2 folders (Box 89)
      - Chapters I-III, draft, typescript revised, and holograph; 2 folders (Box 89)
      - Chapter IV, 1967; draft A, typescript repro, revised; draft B, typescript revised; draft C, typescript revised and holograph; 3 folders (Box 89)
      - Chapter V, 1967; draft A, holograph; draft B, typescript revised; draft C, typescript revised and typescript reproduction revised; draft D, typescript revised; 4 folders (Box 89)
      - Chapter VI, 1967; draft A, holograph and typescript revised; draft B (incomplete), typescript revised; draft C (incomplete), typescript revised; draft D, typescript reproduction; fragments, typescript revised; 5 folders (Box 89)
      - Chapter VII, 1967; draft A, holograph; draft B, typescript revised; 2 folders (Box 90)
      - Chapter VIII, 1967; draft A (incomplete), holograph; draft B (incomplete), holograph and typescript revised; draft C, typescript revised; draft D (incomplete), typescript revised; draft E, typescript reproduction; fragments, typescript revised; 5 folders (Box 90)
      - Chapter IX, 1967; draft, typescript revised; fragments, typescript reproduction; 2 folders (Box 90)
      - Chapter X, 1967; draft A (incomplete), typescript revised, and holograph; draft B (incomplete), typescript revised; fragments, typescript revised; 3 folders (Box 90)
      - Chapter XI, 1967; draft A, typescript revised, and holograph; draft B, typescript revised; fragments, typescript revised, and holograph; 3 folders (Box 90)
      - Chapters I-XI, 1967; fragments, typescript revised, and holograph (Box 90)
      - Chapter XII, 1968; draft A (incomplete), typescript revised, and holograph; draft B, typescript repro, rev.; draft C, typescript repro; 3 folders (Box 90)
      - Afterwords, draft, typescript revised (Box 90)
      - Bibliography, 1968; draft A, holograph; draft B, typescript reproduction and typescript revised; 2 folders (Box 90)
      - Complete draft, Chapters I-XI, 1968; typescript repro; 3 folders (Box 90)
      - Layout of format for book, 1968 (Box 90)
      - Printer's Copy, Sections 1-12, afterword, bibliography, 1968; typescript; 5 folders (Box 91)
      - Galleys, 1968; A, revised (Box 91)
      - Galleys, 1968; B, revised; C, page proofs; D, page proofs E, page proofs; 5 folders (Box 92)
      - Book reviews, 1969; published material (Box 93)
    - Our Christmas Challenge, 1961
      - Foreword, draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 93)
      - Book reviews, published material (Box 93)
    - [On The Parish Church In America?], with John Heuss, 1953; outline, typescript copy (Box 93)
    - Pleading and Procedure in Civil Actions, 1941; typescript copy (Box 93)
    - Roadblocks To Faith, 1955; book reviews, published material (Box 93)
    - A Roman Catholic In The White House, with Richard Byfield, 1960
      - Chapters I-IX, printed material, 2 folders (Box 93)
      - Book reviews, published material, 2 folders (Box 93)
    - Selected Readings on the Legal Profession
      - Research material, holograph and published material (Box 93)
      - Outlines, 1955-1957; typescript, typescript reproduction, typescript copy (Box 93)
      - Chapter X, Sections 1-2, 1960[?]; draft B, typescript copy (Box 93)
      - Chapter X, Sections 3-4, 1960[?]; draft B, typescript copy (Box 94)
      - Chapter X, Section 5, 1957-1960; preliminary material, typescript, typescript copy, printed material, published material; draft B, typescript copy (2 folders) (Box 94)
      - Appendix, 1957-1960; preliminary material, typescript, typescript copy, typescript reproduction, published material (2 folders) (Box 94)
      - Miscellaneous material, 1957-1960; typescript, typescript reproduction, printed material (Box 94)
      - Book reviews, 1963; typescript copy (Box 94)
    - Teen-agers and Sex, research material, drafts, etc; no material relating to chapter V or IX
      - Research material, typescript (Box 94)